Andrei Panferov

ML RESEARCHER

Summary _

I am set to graduate this summer with a Bachelor of Applied Mathematics and Physics from the Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, where I am currently ranked in the top 15 out of more than 200 students in my cohort. I studied Machine Learning at the Yandex School of Data Analysis, and I have a keen interest in Natural Language Processing, efficient Deep Learning and Federated Learning. My achievements range from securing a gold medal at the International Physics Olympiad to making significant contributions to the open-source community, as well as acquiring work experience in both industry and academia.

Experience _____

RESEARCH INTERN

Yandex Research Russia

ML RESEARCH RESIDENT November 2023 - Present

KAUST, Optimization and Machine Learning Lab

July 2023 - September 2023

• Conducted research under the supervision of *Prof. Peter Richtárik*

- Derived theory and ran experiments on distributed optimization, focusing on communication compression
- · Submitted a first-author paper to an upcoming conference, with the preprint soon to be on arXiv (see Publications)

Eqvilent (High Frequency Trading Fund)

Remote

Saudi Arabia

SOFTWARE ENGINEER July 2022 - March 2023

Yandex Russia

ML Engineer Intern (NLP)

March 2022 - July 2022

- Refactored and optimized an LLM inference framework enabling abstract tabular data insertion for efficient map-reduce inference
- Increased test coverage of the map-reduce inference interface from 0 to 85% through rigorous unit testing
- Took part in developing a universal LLM benchmarking solution adapting two datasets for it

Terra Quantum AG Russia

RESEARCHER July 2020 - July 2020

- Researched quantum algorithms for business applications
- Developed an NMR spectra analysis toll, allowing for its use for for quantum computations
- Optimized LLM deployment for chat assistant applications, reducing latency by 40%

Awards _

International Physics Olympiad

Israel

GOLD MEDAL Summer 2019

Education _

Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology (MIPT)

Moscow, Russia

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN APPLIED MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2020 - 2024

- Achieved a perfect 5.0/5.0 GPA
- Second minor in Teaching Methods and Pedagogy
- Working toward my thesis on distributed training of Large Language Models under the supervision of *Prof. Alexander Gasnikov*

Yandex School of Data Analysis (YSDA)

Moscow, Russia

Post-Bachelor's Program in Machine Learning

2021 - 2023

- Completed 12 MSc level courses. Specialized in Deep Learning and Natural Language Processing
- Contributed significantly to *Open-Source* projects (see Open-Source Contributions)
- Served as a TA for the NLP course. Prepared a seminar on Model Compression, challenged the students to implement GPTQ

Publications _____

Correlated Quantization for Faster Nonconvex Distributed Optimization

KAUST, Saudi Arabia

Open-Source Contributions

ntensor_parallel

GITHUB.COM/BLACKSAMOREZ/TENSOR_PARALLEL

- Developed an open-source python library for tensor parallel PyTorch models training and inference tightly integrated with Hugging Face
- Received more than 400 stars on GitHub

LLaMA implementation for transformers

HUGGINGFACE.CO/DOCS/TRANSFORMERS/MAIN/MODEL_DOC/LLAMA

• Took part in adapting the *LLaMA* model for the *Hugging Face transformers* library, fixing the positional embedding errors and optimizing past key-value handling

😕 HuYaLM-100B

HUGGINGFACE.CO/BLACKSAMOREZ/HUYALM-100B-FP16

• Adapted YaLM-100B LLM specifically for Hugging Face transformers, rewriting the officially published Megatron-LM implementation

NLP Bot Project

GITHUB.COM/BLACKSAMOREZ/EBANKO

- Designed an automatic data collection system to extract thousands of dialogues from internet forums, refined the collected data using a pretrained sentiment analysis BERT model and published them it a dataset
- Fine-tuned a GPT-2 model for chatbot purposes on the refined dataset and deployed it as a Telegram bot
- Published an article on Habr (IT social network) about the project, reaching the daily top-1 in the ML section